Guide to the James Cannon III Papers, 1912 - 1974 UA.29.02.0067
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
James Cannon III papers
1912 - 1974
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Cannon, James, 1892-1960
UA.29.02.0067
4.6 Linear Feet
James Cannon III worked as an educator and administrator at Trinity College and Duke University from 1919 to 1960, serving as Dean of the Divinity School from 1951 to 1958. The Canon papers contain correspondence, manuscript drafts of sermons and publications, course materials, subject files, clippings, photographs, ephemera, and scrapbooks relating to the life and work of James Cannon III. Major subjects include biblical literature and the Bible as literature, religious education, missionary training, history of religion, Christianity, Buddhism, comparative religion, and the Cannon family, especially James Cannon, Jr. and James Cannon IV. English.
4,500 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Unprocessed materials are closed pending processing.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The James Cannon III Papers was received by the University Archives as a gift in 1974.
Biographical Note
From 1919 to 1960, Reverend Dr. James Cannon III worked as an educator and administrator at Trinity College and Duke University, serving as Dean of the Divinity School from 1951 to 1958. He was born on November 30, 1892 in Farmville, Virginia to Bishop James Cannon, Jr., and Lura Bennett Cannon. He earned a bachelor's degree from Trinity College in 1914 and a master's degree at Princeton University in 1917. Cannon served in the military as a chaplain during World War I, for which he merited the French Croix de Guerre in 1919. Later that year, he returned to Trinity College to teach Biblical Literature and Missions. While he taught at Trinity, he continued his graduate studies at the Princeton Theological Seminary, earning his bachelor's and master's degrees in theology in 1925. When the Duke University Divinity School opened in 1926, Cannon became the Ivey Professor of the History of Religion and Missions, a position he held until his death on March 9, 1960.
In addition to his work at Duke University, Cannon actively participated in several religious and educational organizations and authored and edited a number of scholarly publications. In 1958, he was elected president of the Association of Methodist Theological Schools. Cannon also served as president of the Professors of Missions in Eastern Universities in 1941. He was secretary of the Duke chapter of Phi Beta Kappa and served on the Phi Beta Kappa National Senate in 1953. He wrote the History of Southern Methodist Missions (Cokesbury Press, 1926) and co-authored A Guide to the Study of the English Bible (Duke University Press, 1926). Cannon also edited periodicals such as Christian Advocate and The Muslim World.
Collection Overview
The Cannon papers were originally organized into three main files and arranged alphabetically within these files. Three series reflecting the original order were created: Personal files and family history, Writings, and Subject files. The Writings series was reorganized by type of writing into three subseries: Sermons, Articles, and Course materials. Some clippings files, reference materials, gradebooks, and duplicates were removed from the papers.
Related Material
Chapel Sermons [sound recordings].
University Archives, Duke University.
James Cannon, Jr. papers.
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Sermons; Bible as literature -- Study and teaching; Buddhism -- Study and teaching; Clippings (information artifacts); Christianity -- Study and teaching -- Sermons; Missions -- Study and teaching; Religion -- History -- Study and teaching; Religions -- Comparative studies; Religious education -- North Carolina; Religious literature; Theological seminaries -- United States; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Duke University -- Faculty; Duke University. Divinity School; Cannon, James, 1864-1944; Cannon, James, 1892-1960; Cannon, James, 1892-1960
- Personal files and family history, 1912-1974
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence, clippings, publications, photographs and ephemera primarily related to Cannon's life and career. Typed note cards within some of the files provide background information on major events and cross-references to other files; a family member or office assistant of Cannon most probably created these. Additional personal and family photographs, clippings, and scrapbooks can be found in Oversize Boxes 10 and 11.
  - Association of Methodist Theological Schools, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Bennett, William Wallace, 1939-1959 (Box 1)
  - Bermuda shorts, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Bishop Cannon's Own Story, 1950-1958 (Box 1)
  - Blackstone, [Virginia], 1960-1965 (Box 1)
  - Cannon, James, Jr., Bishop and Mrs., 1937-1964 (Box 1)
  - Cannon, Walter, 1943-1958, undated (Box 1)
  - Cape Cod, Mass., July 1957 (Box 1)
  - Cards, undated (Box 1)
  - Cartoons, James Cannon III, ca. 1954 (Box 1)
  - Chairman, Duke Divinity School Faculty, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Chaplaincy: Appointment, assignments, identity card, 1918-1919 (Box 1)
  - Citation, United States Army, 1918-1919 (Box 1)
  - Cleland, James T., 1950-1959 (Box 1)
  - Conference, Western North Carolina, 1959-1960 (Box 1)
  - Convocation and James A. Gray Lectures, 1953-1956 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1958-1963 (Box 1)
  - Croix de Guerre, 1919 (Box 1)
  - Cushman, Robert E., 1958-1959 (Box 1)
  - Daily Suggesters [pocket calendars], 1950, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Dean, 1951-1958
    - Appointment as Dean [Congratulatory correspondence]
      - A-J, 1951 (Box 1)
      - K-Z, 1951 (Box 1)
    - Installation as Dean, 1951 (Box 1)
    - Resignation as Dean, 1958 (Box 2)
      - Letters, A-L, 1958-1959 (Box 2)
      - Letters, M-Z, 1958 (Box 2)
    - Deanness, 1951 (Box 2)
  - Death and funeral notices, 1960 (Box 2)
  - Diary, War years, 1918 (Box 2)
  - Discharge, Army, 1918-1919, 1960 (Box 2)
  - Divinity School
    - 1951-1958 (Box 2)
    - 1958-1960 (Box 2)
  - Divinity School students, 1953-1967 (Box 2)
  - Duke Circuit Rider, 1952 (Box 2)
  - Duke Divinity School Bulletin, First editor, 1946 (Box 2)
  - Duke University, 1938-1955, undated (Box 2)
  - Duke in Scotland, 1957 (Box 2)
  - Edens, A. Hollis, President, 1949-1960 (Box 2)
  - Edinburgh [University], 1919 (Box 2)
  - Faculty resolutions on death, 1960 (Box 2)
  - Faculty resolutions on retirement, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Famous Virginians' Dinner, 1957 (Box 3)
  - Federal Council of Churches, 1925 (Box 3)
  - First Division, 1918-1960 (Box 3)
  - Football, undated (Box 3)
  - France and Germany, World War I [photographs and post cards], ca. 1920 (Box 3)
  - Funeral, 1960 (Box 3)
  - Garrett Biblical Institute, 1924 (Box 3)
  - [Graduate Department of Religion], 1959 (Box 3)
  - History of Southern Methodist Missions, 1924-1927 (Box 3)
  - Holy Land [photographs], ca. 1937 (Box 3)
  - Honorary degrees, 1938, 1956 (Box 3)
  - Hope Valley [photographs], undated (Box 3)
  - Ireland, World War I, ca. 1920 (Box 3)
  - Italy, Army YMCA, ca. 1918 (Box 3)
  - Jimmy [James Cannon IV], 1923-ca. 1934 (Box 3)
  - Kendall, Helen M., 1957-1958 (Box 3)
  - Kodak pictures (Assorted) [photographs of James Cannon III], 1938-1959 (Box 3)
  - Library Lectures, Duke Divinity School, 1955, 1959 (Box 3)
  - Memorial service, April 19, 1960 (Box 3)
  - Methodist Theological Seminaries, 1958-1960 (Box 3)
  - Missions, Courses in; Missionary Institutes; Missionary Alumni, 1950-1966 (Box 4)
  - National Cyclopedia of American Biography, 1960-1961 (Box 4)
  - Painting, Lura Bennett Cannon, 1957, undated (Box 4)
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1925, 1957-1960 (Box 4)
  - Photographs, 1914-1960, undated (Box 4)
  - Princeton Theological Seminary, 1915-1917, 1924-1925, 1951 (Box 4)
  - Princeton University, 1924 (Box 4)
  - Princeton University Alumni Association, 1960 (Box 4)
  - Publications, 1925-1931 (Box 4)
  - Publications, 1932-[1958] (Box 4)
  - Randolph-Macon College, 1956 (Box 4)
  - Registration Cards, 1917, 1942 (Box 4)
  - Those Who Remembered, 1960 (Box 4)
  - The Richmond Virginian, 1915 (Box 4)
  - Rocky Mount, North Carolina, 1921 (Box 4)
  - Seminars, Duke Divinity School, 1952-1956 (Box 4)
  - Sigma Chi [certificate of membership], 1912 (Box 4)
  - Spence, H. E., 1942-1963, undated (Box 4)
  - Standard Training Schools, M. E. Church, South, 1922, 1924 (Box 4)
  - The Stars and Stripes, 1918 (Box 4)
  - Stockham, Herbert C., 1958-1960 (Box 4)
  - Supply Pastors' School, Duke Divinity School, 1954-1955 (Box 4)
  - A Tribute to Dean Cannon, 1958 (Box 4)
  - Trinity College, 1913-1955 (Box 4)
  - Wedding, 1920 (Box 4)
  - Who Was Who, 1960 (Box 4)
  - York Chapel, 1951-1958 (Box 4)
  - YMCA -- Army, 1917-1918 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, Margaret Faw, 1917-1919, undated, [5 folders] (Box 5)
  - Automobile accident, 1952 (Box 5)
  - James Cannon Jr.
    - O'Brien-Glass correspondence, other papers in re-trial (Box 5)
  - Guest book from memorial service for James Cannon III, 1960 (Box 5)
  - Reviewers Club, 1974 (Box 5)
- Writings, 1920-1961
  Research notes, manuscript drafts, clippings, programs, and bulletins related to Cannon's sermons, publications, and courses. Additional course-related material can be found in the Subject Files series.
  Arrangement note
  Organized by type of writing into the following subseries: Sermons, Articles, and Course materials; then arranged alphabetically by title within each subseries.
  - Sermons, 1941-1957, undated (Box 6)
    - At Ease with God, Randolph-Macon College Commencement, June 3, 1956 (Box 6)
    - Christ and Human Need, Duke University Church, February 28, 1954 (Box 6)
    - Christian Faith, Duke University Chapel, January 20, 1957 (Box 6)
    - The Christian Message, St. Paul Methodist Church, Durham, N. C., August 5, 1951 (Box 6)
    - The Christian Ministry; or, How Shall They Hear Without a Preacher? 1951 (Box 6)
    - The Consolations of God, Duke University Church, March 15, 1953 (Box 6)
    - The Daily Cross, undated (Box 6)
    - Easter Message, Duke University Chapel, undated (Box 6)
    - Jesus Christ: Who He Was; What He Did, York Chapel Talk, undated (Box 6)
    - Men of Conviction, Duke University Church, January 13, 1952 (Box 6)
    - The Opportunity of a Chain, undated (Box 6)
    - The Pilgrims, Duke University Chapel, July 13, 1952 (Box 6)
    - The Pure Flame of Truth, Phi Beta Kappa address, undated (Box 6)
    - Three Ways of Life: the Communist Way, the American (Democratic) Way, the Christian Way, Duke University Church, July 15, 1951 (Box 6)
    - Truth and Faith, undated (Box 6)
    - When Our Ideals Betray Us, undated (Box 6)
    - Women in Today's World, Columbia College Commencement, 1941 (Box 6)
  - Articles, 1925-1956, undated
    - An Appreciation of the Duke Endowment, North Carolina Christian Advocate, May 31, 1956 (Box 6)
    - Can the Hebrew Old Testament be Relied Upon? undated (Box 6)
    - David Livingstone, undated (Box 6)
    - A Day's Work for a Day's Pay, Christian Advocate, September 4, 1925 (Box 6)
    - The Department of Religious Training, Trinity Alumni Register, undated (Box 6)
    - The Doctrine of the Future Life in India, The Union Seminary Quarterly, January 1926 (Box 6)
    - Every Christian a Missionary, Christian Advocate, June 5, 1925 (Box 6)
    - Figures by Which the Church is Represented in the New Testament, undated (Box 6)
    - The Functions of a College Department of Missions, North Carolina Christian Advocate, May 14, 1925 (Box 6)
    - Future Life among Animistic Peoples, Methodist Quarterly Review, October 1925 (Box 6)
    - The Gospel of Barnabus, The Moslem World, April 1942 (Box 6)
    - Habakkuk, a Monograph on Faith, Nashville Christian Advocate, February 19, 1926 (Box 6)
    - Investment Opportunity, North Carolina Christian Advocate, August 16, 1951 (Box 6)
    - Japanese Indigenous Christianity, South Atlantic Quarterly, July 1925 (Box 6)
    - The Linguistic Argument for the Late Date of Canticles, Methodist Quarterly Review, April 1925 (Box 6)
    - Methodist Theological Schools Are Growing, North Carolina Christian Advocate, July 31, 1952 (Box 6)
    - Missionary Education at the Home Base, The Missionary Review of the World, April 1926 (Box 6)
    - Missionary Families, undated (Box 6)
    - The Order of the Green Mustaches, [Poem], undated (Box 6)
    - Our Missionary Literature, Christian Advocate, March 13, 1925 (Box 6)
    - The Philosophy of Missions, World Outlook, April 1952 (Box 7)
    - Proofs of the Christian Life, Christian Advocate, July 9, 1926 (Box 7)
    - The Search for Saviors, undated (Box 7)
    - Shinto: Literary Sources and Popular Cultus, The Review and Expositor, July 1925 (Box 7)
    - The Teaching of Missions in Colleges, Christian Advocate, March 27, 1925 (Box 7)
    - Transmigration and Karma in Hinduism, undated (Box 7)
    - The Vital Breath of Missions, North Carolina Christian Advocate, August 16, 1928 (Box 7)
    - Who Should Pay for Educating Methodist Ministers? Virginia Methodist Advocate, Nov. 23, 1950 (Box 7)
    - Will We Run Out of Preachers? Shepherds, April 1952 (Box 7)
    - The Witness of the Roman Catacombs to Early Christianity, New York Christian Advocate, undated (Box 7)
    - The World Outlook of Duke University, World Outlook, July 1941 (Box 7)
  - Course materials, 1920-1960, undated
    - The Bible as literature, Summer school, undated (Box 7)
    - The Bible, The use of in public schools, Summer school, ca. 1920 (Box 7)
    - Bo tree, 1944-1951 (Box 7)
    - Buddhism, Miscellaneous, 1929-1933 (Box 7)
    - Buddhism in Ceylon, Burma, Cambodia, Siam, undated (Box 7)
    - Buddhism in China, ca. 1929 (Box 7)
    - Buddhism in India, undated (Box 7)
    - Buddhism in Japan, undated (Box 7)
    - Christianity and world movements, undated (Box 7)
    - The Church on the mission field, ca. 1947 (Box 7)
    - College courses in missions, 1929, 1949 (Box 7)
    - Divinity School, early days, 1926 (Box 7)
    - Divinity School faculty, 1926-1958 (Box 7)
    - Ethical ideals and social practice in the religions of the world (Comparative Religion), undated (Box 8)
    - Expansion of Christianity to the Reformation, Summer school, ca. 1920 (Box 8)
    - Great preachers and missionaries, undated (Box 8)
    - Ideas of future life [Religion 284: Comparative Religion], ca. 1941 (Box 8)
    - The idea of God, Comparative Religion, ca. 1945 (Box 8)
    - The idea of salvation, Comparative Religion, undated (Box 8)
    - The idea of sin (Comparative Religion), ca. 1942 (Box 8)
    - Hinduism, 1940-1950 (Box 8)
    - How religions have spread, undated (Box 8)
    - Judaism, ca. 1947 (Box 8)
    - Latin America, Christian work in, ca. 1936 (Box 8)
    - Missionary education, suggested program for a local church, ca. 1944 (Box 8)
    - Missions in the modern world, 1935-1960 (Box 8)
    - The nature and early development of religion [Religion 181], undated (Box 8)
    - Preaching, Expository, undated (Box 8)
    - Religions of Eastern Asia, China, Korea, Japan, ca. 1943 (Box 8)
    - Religions of India, Religion S285, 1939-1947 (Box 8)
    - Rise and expansion of Islam, undated (Box 8)
    - Superstitions, ca. 1949 (Box 8)
    - Theological scholarships, ca. 1950 (Box 8)
- Subject files, 1917-1965
  Research notes, correspondence, clippings, and other materials related to Dr. Cannon's teaching and writing. Some files contain outlines for courses included in the Course materials subseries above.
  - Africa, ca. 1943 (Box 9)
  - Program of Advance in Foreign Ministries, October 1948 (Box 9)
  - Chronology of China, undated (Box 9)
  - Cleland, James T., 1955-1965 (Box 9)
  - Comparative religion, Outlines, undated (Box 9)
  - Garber, Bishop and Mrs. Paul N., 1947-1963 (Box 9)
  - Garber diary
    - February 10, 1945 - October 5, 1945 (Box 9)
    - October 11, 1945 - March 12, 1946 (Box 9)
    - March 13, 1946 - December 15, 1946 (Box 9)
    - March 22, 1947 - September 4, 1947 (Box 9)
  - Hindu sacred literature, course notes, undated (Box 9)
  - History of Religion 15, Examination, 1951 (Box 9)
  - Islam, lecture notes, ca. 1939 (Box 9)
  - Living religions, course outline, undated (Box 9)
  - The philosophy of the Christian world mission, lecture notes, 1946-1951 (Box 9)
  - Mohammedanism - Outline, ca. 1946
    - Bibliography, undated (Box 9)
    - Clippings, ca. 1945 (Box 9)
  - Nature and Development of Religion [Religion 181], undated (Box 9)
  - Petry, Ray C., 1950-1964 (Box 9)
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1960 (Box 9)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 9)
  - Schweitzer, Albert [Clippings], 1947 (Box 9)
  - World mission of the Christian religion, course, ca. 1930 (Box 9)
- Oversize materials
  - The Book of Jimmy Cannon (Box 10)
    This scrapbook details the life of James Cannon IV, son of James Cannon III. The book contains photographs, ephemera, correspondence and other materials.
  - Scrapbook (Box 11)
  - Photographs (Box 11)
  - Clippings (Box 11)